So, I have some questions sent in from a
friend. He's wondering if you could
answer them for
him. He says, "I find myself stuck in a
recurring cycle. I act wholesomely for a
while, then gradually act in minor unh
wholesome ways, which eventually
escalate into more significant
act. Afterwards, I'm filled with regret
and return to acting wholesomely only
for the pattern to repeat. And right
now, I'm in the regret stage, fully
aware that I sabotage myself
intentionally. I feel the urge to double down on my
I feel the urge to double down on my
efforts to break the cycle. But that's
exactly what I always do. And it never
seems to lead to real progress. How can
I genuinely move forward rather than
just going in circles?
Well, the thing
is as a as a
householder living in already
compromised environment going in
circles is a way of
progressing. So you will not have a
clean break because you're not making a
clean break from the environment.
So that's not you know I'm not trying to
to justify the failure but I'm just
saying it's
inevitable. So it's important because
sometimes people can can get um
frustrated in a sense of thinking but
surely I must like just have like a like
you know a clean determination. They
will they will create like a clean sort
of ending of these unh wholesome states
and ways of acting. It's not going to
happen. You're going to build up a
determination. You're going to keep up
with it. You're going to be restrained.
and you're going to be paying attention
to the intentions behind your actions
and then you're going to fail cuz you're
going to start slipping because the
environment is
compromising. When you slip the remorse,
the regret, it's part of the progress.
So, it's important to then not try to
psychologize that away and justify or
even worse fall into a view that no, I
shouldn't be even trying to restrain. I
shouldn't be even trying to break this
this vicious cycle. But it's through
going through the vicious cycle
internally, you are kind of making the
effort. So you can't unless you change
your environment
drastically, you will be failing and you
have to accept that you're going to feel
miserable on account of
it. That will then help you build a
termination better. That will then help
you become even more familiar with your
intentions and then you're going to fail
again and then you're going to repeat
and then you're going to fail again and
then you're going to repeat and that's
how you are actually getting closer to
um not falling back as much as you used
to. Now do you have time for such a
Now do you have time for such a
practice? How long can you s sustain? Do
you have 50 years of that slow progress of
have 50 years of that slow progress of
constant failure and stuff? It might
make some difference by the end of it,
but it might not. You might run out of
time. So there is that risk as well that
you have to accept. So if you can try
and shape your environment as much as
you can so it's supporting so that when
you start slipping you don't slip as far
because simply you don't have access to
things that that make you slip as far.
You have to foresee that.
So you start to notice the little things
that you know all these minor acts that
you do that lead to this exactly
breakdown. Yeah. So you're trying that
add up add up add up and then eventually
when the breakdown starts happening you
have no means of stopping it because you
already built up the momentum from
before and honesty the whole time you
know honest like oh when I I'm watching
TV and entertainment break precepts yeah
and so on and then then where where does
that lead eventually well yeah all of
those reflections will have to be
obviously cultivated effectively but the
thing is with all of had as I said the
environment is already compromising. So
you will be even with all the
reflections and all the thinking all the
right things the time will come when
it's just going to get too much and you
will willingly give
in. You can be relaxing, you can be
focusing, you can be doing this, you
could be doing that all the coping
mechanisms but the point is none the
time will come when things build up none
of that will work. And the only reason
you're not failing is because there's
nothing for you to to to give into. It's
too far. And then by the time you were
to to reach things, you give into uh the
mind would have changed and then you
wouldn't okay past especially in the
beginning. Especially in the
beginning. So you really need to
recognize that environment and foresee
when your mind is leading you in that
direction where you're gradually giving
in and then just uh prevent yourself
from ending up in that environment where
you have a quick access to things that
would compromise the
precepts. So it's it comes down to that
uh
physical separation. So things are
further removed. Access to entertainment
is further removed. Access to things
that provoke you to act with lust or
anger are further removed when the
crisis sets in. And that will actually
provide you some well that will prevent
you from falling back as far as you
would have otherwise.
And that needs to be developed
beforehand recognizing the little signs
and features that lead up towards it.
But if that's been uh carefully sort of
um tailored, shaped
uh pushed away a bit beforehand, then
that will offer you some space.
It's and so you've you've got that space
those norm those common things you don't
have access to anymore.
But you still have access to your body.
You still have access to your mind.
Yeah. So you're thinking so
that you can't run away from. No. And
that's like those things you should be
developing before it gets too much
before the mind is too wound up with
lust or anger or distraction before you
would have reached the point of acting
out and now you're remorseful. So when
things are fine when you have some as I
said some room for reflection room for
space room for like discerning your
intentions and contemplating them that's
what you're recognizing. Hold on. Yes.
Okay, now I'm
conditionally temporarily safe because
the most pressing sight sounds smell
taste touches that would provoke me one
way or the other are further removed.
But that doesn't mean I'm actually safe.
It just means I've kind of postponed the
danger. So what do I do now? Well, while
I'm safe now, I should definitely be
cultivating uh and discerning the that
internal relationship with my own body
and my own mind, mind and the body. So
how does my mind does my mind still
regard this body as as um as belonging
to it? Is my mind still um
implicitly taking the body to be the
source of possible pleasure pleasure
that is worthy to pursue? Is my mind uh
forgetting the lack of safety that's
inherent in this physical form and the
body? So those contemplations that's
when you do them. When the mind is just
completely wild, doesn't want to listen
to you, then you just need a physical
separation until it calms down. None of
this will work.
But of course, yes, if you invest the
right effort before the mind winds up
itself way too much, it might not wind
up wind itself up that much because
these perceptions that you're providing
for the mind, unknownability of the
body, knowing your intentions, the
danger, foreseeing the environment that
could compromise you, all of that. It's
kind of telling right things to that
mind. It's showing it, okay, you know,
this is better for you as well. And you
you will get to see it for yourself. the
animal will see for itself that actually
yeah this is actually better than um
than giving into thirst, passion, anger,
distraction, entertainment, delighting
in the body. Delighting in the body.
Yeah. So then if if you are if you are
developing that right perspective in
regard to your body while you're not
kind of acutely pressured then you get
to discern as well. Okay. So mentally
when images and thoughts of of
sensuality or ill will or cruelty how to
say or conceit they come up in the same
sense side statues come up but am I
accepting them do I just feel like oh I
just they're mine as soon as they come
up why is that so that's when you could
then introduce that layer of mental
purification um and that's also what's going to
um and that's also what's going to
shift, you know, like initially people's
restraint will be mechanical. It's just
going to be saying no to stuff, but
that's that's not even the right
restraint. That's just how you have to
start. Sure. But yes, once you okay, you
said no to certain things, to certain
environments, to certain compromising
situations, you foresee them, you don't
give in, you don't go there. Then by
recognizing, okay, so now there is the
internal relationship with this body. Is
it taken through the sense of ownership?
Taken as a basis of pleasure, taken as a
basis of safety, mastery, control.
That's already now the right restraint.
In other words, that restraint is now
really not anymore like restraint in
that blind mechanical manner. It's uh
it's already a way of
purification. That's when the restraint
becomes purification. And then same you
recognize what thoughts are coming up,
what thoughts are enduring, what
thoughts are sort of persisting, what
thoughts well what thoughts are kind of
indicating the state of the animal, the
state of the mind, the state of the
chitta because you wouldn't have
thoughts of
anger coming up and besetting you,
images associated with such thoughts if
the mind is not angry. If the mind is
not at least to some degree
irritated or or
resistant doesn't matter how ambiguous
that mood might be you could get to
discern okay so if these are thoughts
that are revolving it's because mind is
kind of leaning in that direction so
what do you do well I need to show the
animal I need to I need to show it that
this is not beneficial so you can't stop
the thoughts but you could then as we
said before okay I will not welcome it
yes these thoughts keep coming up I want
allowed in the center stage. I won't
welcome them. And that's already, see,
although it's still like you're
restraining the allowance, the delight
towards the thoughts, really, you're
already purifying. You're already
sending a message to the animal that's
much more than just restraint. That's
much more than just saying
no. Because the sole reason the animal
is still wild is because you were
welcoming such thoughts. welcoming the
root of the problem, welcoming the sense
of ownership, lust, aversion, whenever
when these thoughts come up, you don't
see an option for them to not be uh
delighted in. And that's also why people
fall into that trap of trying to deny or
replace thoughts. They don't see the
mind behind
it. Any thought is not a problem in
itself. It's a problem of the state of
the mind of the animal that's implicit
in it. So that's why if your sole
concern is to replace the thoughts the
the state of the animal doesn't change
because you haven't even seen it to
begin with. So say mind is angry you
start have angry thoughts and then as a
result of that you want to replace those
thoughts and think positive thoughts on
account of an angry mind
and that's it and you have not seen the
actual you have not conveyed the message
that the mind the animal the chitta can
understand but if such thoughts are
coming up or thoughts of sensuality you
can't have thoughts of sensuality if the
mind is not leaning towards uh
delighting and craving the sensual
pleasure But that's not your problem directly.
But that's not your problem directly.
It's not that you are doing that. You're
a victim of it in a way. But given that
it's just you and the mind, whether
you're a victim or not on paper, you are
the one who pays the price. So you want
to start taking responsibility. Yes, I'm
not doing this. It's the mind doing it.
But it doesn't absolve me from
tolerating it. That's the
point because it's only me that's going
to be affected by this. So then I won't
tolerate it. So how you not tolerate it?
Well, when sensual thoughts are coming
up, you recognize, okay, so the mind is
central. Even if the central thoughts
stop coming up, even if you replace them
with whatever, you still know, hold on.
But those thoughts wouldn't have come up
if the animal is not already wanting
that. So even if you replace the
thoughts or not, it was not about the
thoughts, it was about the state of the
mind behind it.
So that's why it's like okay so when
these thoughts are coming up I won't
just blindly welcome them accept them
try to get rid of them or indulge them
even worse I will not lose the sight of
the mind behind
it and as I said before when those
thoughts are coming up in regards to
sensuality and your will you already
know where they would lead what those
thoughts will crystallize
towards so the point is then like Okay.
So there is this pressure there is the
inclination to allow thoughts that will
become sensual to allow thoughts that
will become ill will or conceit or
cruelty or any associated with any
hindrance. That's what I won't do by not
allowing that that last drop last focus
on aha this is the thought I'm taking it
up literally by unfocusing from that
degree. You are staying on the level
where your mind is. You are staying with
the level where the animal is. And then
you get to see how the animal is really
wanting you to accept these thoughts.
And by not accepting them, you are
conveying the message. The only reason
animal is still trying to present you
with these
thoughts is because you've been
inadvertently always accepting them. So
it works. It knows it works. And then
you start acting towards it. And then
you start feeding the animal with
unsuitable food. And in the end he got
he got what he wanted. He made you act.
Yeah. So by not accepting those thoughts
saying it gets the message that it
doesn't work anymore. Yeah. That doesn't
Yeah. And that's the similar so many
similarities in the sutas where the
Buddha gave like you know the the jackal
and the turtle.
It surrounds the
turtle and it's like you can't escape
it. You can't escape. You are
surrounded. You you and the wild animal.
That's all there is from your point of
view as far as you're concerned. So you
can't, oh, I'll just go elsewhere and
leave the jackal behind. No. And the
simile goes on. The turtle, if he tries
to, you know, extend its limbs and
escape, the jackal will get it. Doesn't
matter if I extend the limb to to
approve the jackal or to to push it
away, I'm going to get bitten. That's
all he wants. He wants an engagement.
So the whole simile is about not
extending the limbs until the jackal
goes away. In this case the jackal is the
away. In this case the jackal is the
wild animal.
So you should not act by body by speech
mentally allowing the center stage of
thoughts that you know what they will
crystallize towards until the mind
behind it doesn't change until the mind behind
it doesn't change until the mind behind
it does not turn away from what he
wanted. And when he does, then you're
fine. Then you can walk away because the
jackal has
left. But if your sole concern is to
just mechanically deny thoughts, replace
them, go through the visualizations and
stuff, that still means you're
identifying animal with your thoughts.
You don't even see the difference. You
haven't even seen the chitta for what it
is. And that's why there will be no
development. That's why even the sense
restraint will not turn into
purification. It's just going to become
mechanical. Is it going to remain
mechanical saying no to stuff?
It won't turn into purification. It
won't become purification. No. So sense
of restraint to see where the where the
real dirt is. Well, sense restraint done
rightly becomes basically purification
by body, speech and mind.